Finding Aid for Sierra Club. Michigan Chapter records, 1964-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sierra Club. Michigan Chapter records
1964-2007
1975-2005
Sierra Club. Michigan Chapter.
91448 Bn 2
Environmental conservation and protection advocacy group founded in 1967 as the Mackinac Chapter of the Sierra Club, name later changed to Michigan Chapter; administrative, legislative, and topical files.
21 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Michigan Chapter of the Sierra Club (Donor No. 7878 ) beginning in 1990.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Founded in California in 1892, the Sierra Club was originally organized by John Muir and a small group of San Francisco professionals and businessmen concerned with preserving the natural features of the Sierra Nevada region. Over the next 70 years, the Sierra Club promoted the establishment and extension of national parks and forests and opposed activities that would alter wilderness areas such as the construction of hydro-electric dams and the cutting of old-growth forests. After years of battle and many regional successes, the Sierra Club was buoyed by congressional passage of the Wilderness Act in 1964. This act prohibited development in specific wilderness areas and established procedures for designating other such areas in the future.
While wilderness protection continued to be a major area of concern, the Sierra Club gradually became more involved in a wider range of environmental issues after the mid-1960s. In 1969, the San Francisco office won a suit to stop pollution in Lake Superior and, aligned with other national environmental groups, the Sierra Club fought successfully to ban the domestic use of DDT in 1972 and called for the closure of all commercial nuclear reactors in 1979. In 1980, the national office supported "Superfund" legislation designed to clean up toxic waste dumps. In that same year, the Sierra Club became involved in electoral politics for the first time and, during 1981 and 1982, the club organized a petition drive to oust Interior Secretary James Watt. Throughout the 1980s, the Sierra Club continued to encourage wilderness preservation and to strengthen clean air and water standards.
The history of the Mackinac chapter began in 1964 when a group, composed mainly of those hailing from Ann Arbor, gathered to establish a Michigan chapter of the Sierra Club. First organized as the Michigan Section of the Great Lakes Chapter (1964-1967), the national office gave formal approval for the establishment of a separate Michigan chapter in 1967 and the Mackinac Chapter was born. At that point, the chapter included 420 members, most of who lived in southeast Michigan.
During the early years, the business of developing a fledgling organization preoccupied the chapter. Outings and educational programs were popular and attracted new members. However, issue-oriented activity was not neglected. In 1968, the chapter urged the establishment of the Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore and fought against the construction of the Presque Isle power plant in the Upper Peninsula.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, the dual agenda of the Mackinac Chapter was similar to that of the Sierra Club nationally: to protect wilderness areas and to urge the state to control pollution more effectively. The chapter lobbied for the Michigan Wilderness Act that in 1987 finally resulted in the designation of some 90,000 acres as wilderness area. Members were keen supporters of legislation designed to protect wetlands and the fragile sand dunes along the Great Lakes. The Mackinac Chapter also supported restrictions on some types of activities within national and state forests such as off-road vehicle use and mineral exploration.
Aligned with other Michigan environmental groups, the chapter pressed for more stringent pollution controls. Whether dealing with the construction of new paper mills or the disposal of low-level radioactive waste, the Mackinac Chapter urged sensitivity to the environmental impact of such activities. Several issues absorbed the chapter throughout the late 1980s and into the 1990s, including the incineration of municipal waste (namely the Detroit Incinerator, the chapter urged the Environmental Protection Agency and the Department of Natural Resources to monitor more closely air emissions and the disposal of the toxic ash from this facility), the reorganization of the Department of Natural Resources by Governor Engler, and the land and resource management plan of the Huron-Manistee National Forest.
The Mackinac Chapter of the Sierra Club has expanded from a small, local group of conservationists to a statewide organization representing over 18,000 members. Current campaigns of interest include forest biodiversity protection, concentrated animal feeding operations, urban sprawl, healthcare without harm, and restoring state environmental stewardships. The chapter continues to take action on these issues through lobbying, litigation, grassroots organizing, public education and political action. The Mackinac Chapter is headquartered in Lansing and several local groups campaign for environmental issues throughout the state. Groups include Central Michigan, Central Upper Peninsula, Crossroads, Huron Valley, Kalamazoo Valley, Nepessing, Southeast Michigan, Three Lakes, Thumb Valley, Traverse Group, Wakelin-McNeel, and West Michigan. More information about the chapter can be found on its website at www.michigan.sierraclub.org.
In 2006 the chapter changed its name from the Mackinac Chapter to the Michigan Chapter. The chapter celebrated its 40th anniversary in October 2007.
The records of the Michigan Chapter of the Sierra Club document the activities of this state affiliate of the national organization as well as the general environmental movement in Michigan. The series in the record group are: Executive Committee Records, Administrative Records, Department of Natural Resources (DNR), Health Issues, Land Issues, Legislation, Topical, and Audio/Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Land use--Michigan.; Michigan. Dept. of Natural Resources.; Refuse and refuse disposal--Michigan.; Sierra Club. Michigan Chapter.; Salvage (Waste, etc.)--Michigan.; Wetlands--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.
- Executive Committee Records, 1964-1989
  The Executive Committee Records includes minutes of executive committee meetings as well as a range of other documents including correspondence, reports, flyers, and press releases. All of this material was received and maintained in chronological order for the period from 1964 to 1987 with scattered records for 1988-1989. For the first twenty years of the Mackinac Chapter (1964-1984), this series is probably the most complete record of its organizational activity.
  - 1964-1987, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - 1988-1989 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Administrative Files, 1989-1994
  The Administrative Files series contains information regarding the operation of the chapter. Folders that may be of interest to researchers include the various committees' meeting minutes. Although scattered in date and not as comprehensive as the Executive Committee Records series, these materials consistently highlight events and activities of importance at the state level. Additional materials of interest may be found in the Grant Information folder, which contains details about many of the projects for which the chapter has sought financial support, and the Treasury Reports folder.
  - Accreditation, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Awards, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Budget, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Bulk Mailing Permits, undated (Box 6)
  - Canvassing Project, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Centennial Celebration
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Program Information, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Chapter Bylaws, undated (Box 6)
  - Class Lecture Materials, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Committee Meeting Minutes, etc. (scattered)
    - Conservation Committee, 1990-1994 (Box 6)
    - Executive and Steering Committee, 1989-1994 (Box 6)
    - Political Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Director's Reports, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Donor Information, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Executive Committee Member (unidentified) Binder Contents, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Fundraising Information, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Grant Information, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Groups (correspondence, mission statements, etc.)
    - Crossroads, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Salk Trail, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Three Lakes, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Windago, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Group Boundary Committee, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Group Needs Assessment, undated (Box 6)
  - Inner City Outings (ICO), 1989-1992 (Box 6)
  - Legal Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Legislative District Coordinator Handbook and Information, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Membership Information
    - General, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - Nepessing Group, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990-1994 (Box 6)
  - Modem Information, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Nominating/Elections Committee, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
  - Personnel, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Personnel Information (Job Descriptions), 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Political Activist Training, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Stephen G. Porter Estate, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Resumes, circa 1991 (Box 6)
  - Retreat Participants, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Treasury Reports (scattered), 1990-1994 (Box 6)
  - Tree Contest Winners, 1989-1991 (Box 6)
  - General, 1999-2003 (Box 6)
- Department of Natural Resources (DNR)
  The Department of Natural Resources series documents the chapter's interaction and relationship with the DNR and its policies toward specific animals. Many of the files relate to the reorganization of the department in the 1990s.
  - Bears, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Deer, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Directors
    - Gordon E. Guyer, 1988 (Box 6)
    - David Hales, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Endangered Species, 1987-1992 (Box 6)
  - Non-Game Check Off (Box 6)
  - Moose, 1987; 1992 (Box 6)
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Reorganization
    - Notes, undated (Box 6)
    - Plans and Executive Orders, 1984-1991 (Box 6)
    - Testimony, Comments and Notes, 1984-1994 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1988-1995 (Box 6)
    - Opposition Strategy, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Conservation Group Resolutions/Recommendations, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Executive Order Litigation, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
    - Clippings and Press Releases, 1991-1995 (Box 7)
    - Sierra Club Correspondence, 1991-1995 (Box 7)
  - Wolves and Coyotes (Box 7)
  - General (Box 7)
- Health Issues
  The Health Issues series cover a variety of topics related to the impact of pollution on human health. The series is further divided into three subseries: Air Quality, Detroit Incinerator, and Waste Management. Material on these topics will also be found throughout the records.
  - Air Quality
    - Air Free Committee, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Acid Rain, 1981-1992 (Box 7)
    - Air Toxins, 1988-1992 (Box 7)
    - Air Workgroup/Alison Horton, 1991-1994 (Box 7)
    - Auto Emissions, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Clean Air Act, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
    - Clean Air Network, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Clippings (Clean Air Act), 1993 (Box 7)
    - Detroit News Articles, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Dioxins, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Emissions Trading Workgroup, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Enforcement Workgroup, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Global Warming, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    - Incinerator Emissions Regulations, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Operating Permit Workgroup, 1993-1994 (Box 7)
    - Sources of Air Toxics, 1900 (Box 7)
    - Start-Up/Shut-Down Workgroup, 1993-1994 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Detroit Incinerator
    - "Chronology of Detroit,", 1984-1986 (Box 8)
    - Clippings, 1990-1994 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence
      - Combustion Engineering to Wayne County Public Health Department, 1989 (Box 8)
      - Greater Detroit Resource Recovery Authority, 1989 (Box 8)
      - Wayne County Public Health Department, Air Pollution Control Div., 1989 (Box 8)
      - Sierra Club Internal, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Court Cases, 1989-1994 (Box 8)
    - Deposition of Anne Woiwode, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Deposition Exhibits 13-50, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Emissions and Incinerator Testing, 1988-1990 (Box 8)
    - EPA Publications, 1987-1990 (Box 8)
    - Finances, 1987-1992 (Box 8)
    - Lawsuit Settlement Information, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
    - Legislation, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Media Coverage, 1986-1990 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Air Pollution Control Commission Meeting, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1986-1991 (Box 8)
    - Notes, circa 1990 (Box 8)
  - Waste Management
    - Benzie County Incinerator, 1993 (Box 9)
    - "Beverage Container Bill" (PA 148), 1982-1991 (Box 9)
    - Bond and Loan Bills, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Clean Michigan Fund, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations (CAFOs)
      - Bio Fuels, 2006 (Box 9)
      - Litigation, 2000-2001 (Box 9)
      - Michigan State University, 2005-2006 (Box 9)
      - General, 2001-2008 (Box 9)
    - Greater Detroit Resource and Recovery Authority (GDRRA) Settlement, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Hazardous Materials List, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Hazardous Waste Management Plan, 1988-1991 (Box 9)
    - Incinerators, circa, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Incinerator Ash, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Landfill Sites, 1988-1991 (Box 9)
    - Low-Level Radioactive Waste, 1977-1991 (Box 9)
    - Macomb County Solid Waste Management Plan, 1988-1990 (Box 9)
    - Medical Waste Incinerators, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Ash
      - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
      - FOIA Documents from the DNR, 1989 (Box 9)
      - Press Release, 1989 (Box 10)
      - Research, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - General, 1989; 2001 (Box 10)
    - Recycling, 1983-1991 (Box 10)
    - Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA), 1991 (Box 10)
    - Right to Know/Right to Act, 1987-1988 (Box 10)
    - Risk Assessment Guidelines, 1990-1991 (Box 10)
    - "Solid Waste Management Act" (PA 641), 1979-1994 (Box 10)
    - Solid Waste Management Policy, 1988-1991 (Box 10)
    - Solid Waste Workshop Information, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Superfund Information, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Toxic Release Inventory (TRI), 1989-1991 (Box 10)
    - Wayne County Landfills, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Waste-to-Energy Facilities, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Woodland Meadows Recycling and Solid Waste Facility Expansion, 1991-1993 (Box 10)
    - Wurtsmith Air Force Base, 1991 (Box 10)
- Land Issues
  The Land Issues series has been divided into several subseries: Land Management, National Lands, State Lands, and Wetlands. Many of the files relate to individual parks and forest reserves.
  - Land Management
    - Boren/Bryant Bill, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Chequamegon National Forest, 1986 (Box 10)
    - Forestry
      - Litigation, 1998-2002 (Box 10)
      - Michigan Forestry Legacy Program, 2002 (Box 10)
      - General, 1993-2003 (Box 10)
      - Workshops
        - Activists Workshop on Forestry and Biodiversity, 1994 (Box 10)
        - Michigan Forest Activist, 1998 (Box 10)
        - Midwest Forest Practices, 1991 (Box 11)
        - Shaping Tomorrow's Forests Today, 1996 (Box 11)
        - Speaking for the Trees, 1994 (Box 11)
    - Forest Watch, 1990 (Box 11)
    - Grand Island Project
      - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
      - General Information, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
    - Hiawatha National Forest
      - Borrowed Time, 1993-1997 (Box 11)
      - Grand Is, 1988-1994 (Box 11)
      - Grand Island Draft Environmental Impact Statement (Box 11)
      - Old Growth, 1991-1995 (Box 11)
      - Plan Agreement and Amendments, 1987-1990 (Box 11)
    - Huron-Manistee National Forest
      - Analysis of Au Sable River Opportunity Area, circa 1992 (Box 11)
      - Drew Barton Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 11)
      - Friends of the Forest, 1989-1990 (Box 11)
      - Harrisville Ranger District, 1989-1994; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Land and Resource Management Plan
        - Responsive Statement, 1986 (Box 12)
        - Appeal, 1986 (Box 12)
        - Settlement
          - Proposals and Final, 1986-1988 (Box 12)
          - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
      - Old Growth, 1993-1999 (Box 12)
      - Overview, 1997-1998 (Box 12)
      - Plan Implementation and Settlement, 1986-1997 (Box 12)
      - Pontiac Fiberboard Development, 1993 (Box 12)
      - Statement of Appeal, 1987; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Walkinshaw Wetlands, 1993-1994 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1989-1994 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Forest Activist Workshop, 1996-1998 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Forest Practices Act
      - General Correspondence and Notes, 1989-1994 (Box 13)
      - Michigan's Forest Laws, 1990 (Box 13)
      - Ad Hoc Committee Correspondence/Notes, 1991-1993 (Box 13)
      - Drafts, Comments and Proposals, 1991-1993 (Box 13)
    - Midwest Forest Practices Workshop Packet, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Midwest Forestry Training Weekend, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Mulligan Creek Logging Plans, 1993 (Box 13)
    - National Forest Committee, Mackinac Chapter, 1991-1993 (Box 13)
    - Nordhouse Dunes, 1988-1994 (Box 13)
    - Ottawa National Forest
      - Plan and Litigation, 1997-2002 (Box 13)
      - Statement of Appeal (Box 13)
    - Pere Marquette State Forest, 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Sand Dunes Management, 1989-1991 (Box 13)
    - Tower Mountain, 1989 (Box 13)
      (includes photographs)
    - U.S. Highway 23, 1994 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Presque Isle County Pulp Mill, 1990 (Box 13)
    - Publications of the Sierra Club, Mackinac Chapter, 1991-1994 (Box 13)
    - Rails to Trails Conservancy, 1990 (Box 13)
    - Sierra Club Mackinac Chapter National Forest Management Sub-Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 13)
    - State Forest Information, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Takings Legislation
      - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1994-1995 (Box 13)
      - Takings Activist Workshop, 1995 (Box 13)
      - Clippings, 1995 (Box 13)
    - Timber Prices and Sales, 1993 (Box 13)
    - Timber Sale Litigation
      - Correspondence, Communication to Sierra Club, 1994 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, Press Releases from Sierra Club, 1994 (Box 13)
      - Press Clippings, 1994 (Box 13)
      - Judge Collette Ruling, 1995 (Box 13)
  - National Lands
    - Forest Wilderness
      - Acts and Bills, 1978-1988 (Box 13)
      - Big Island Lakes, 1991 (Box 13)
      - Carp River (Box 13)
      - Eastern Wilderness Information, 1988 (Box 13)
      - Handicappers (Box 13)
      - Implementation, 1988-1991 (Box 13)
        (Michigan Wilderness legislation)
      - McCormick, 1990 (Box 13)
      - Nordhouse Dunes (Box 13)
      - Recreation (Box 13)
      - Rock River Canyon, 1993 (Box 13)
      - Round Island (Box 13)
      - Sturgeon River, 1990 (Box 13)
      - Sylvania, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
      - Wildlife Management (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous, 1978-1997; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Parks
      - Isle Royale, 1957-1999 (Box 14)
      - North Country Trail, 1990-1993 (Box 14)
      - Picture Rocks, 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Sleeping Bear Dunes, 1970-1995 (Box 14)
      - South Manitou Is, 1988; 1991 (Box 14)
      - General, 1987-1993 (Box 14)
        (proposals, annual reports, etc.)
    - Wildlife Refuges (Box 14)
  - State Lands
    - Biking, 1991-1992 (Box 14)
    - Camp Grayling, 1989-1994 (Box 14)
    - DNR Recreation Planning, 1991-1996 (Box 14)
    - Forests
      - Escanaba, 1990-1992 (Box 14)
      - Mackinac, 1991 (Box 14)
      - Pere Marquette, 1992 (Box 14)
    - Forest Development Plan, 1989-1990 (Box 14)
    - Forest Planning, 1980-1992 (Box 14)
    - Forest Practices, 1990 (Box 14)
    - Forestry Pulp Mills, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
    - Forest Products (MI) Industry council, 1988; 1991 (Box 14)
    - Forestry-Miscellaneous, 1986-1991 (Box 15)
    - Land Trust Fund Information, 1988 (Box 15)
    - Off Road Vehicles (ORV), 1984-1991; 2003 (Box 15)
    - Oil and Gas Issues, 1970-1991 (Box 15)
    - Rails to Trails, 1988 (Box 15)
    - State Parks
      - Advisory Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 15)
      - Grand Traverse (Box 15)
      - Highland Recreation Area, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Island State Park ORVs, 1988-1990 (Box 15)
      - Management, 1987-1996 (Box 15)
      - Negwegon (Box 15)
      - Recreation Programs, 1989-1994 (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
        (various maps, directories, etc.)
    - Trails, maps (Box 15)
    - Trail Legislation, 1968; 1988 (Box 15)
  - Wetlands
    - Au Sable River, 1988-1990 (Box 15)
    - Dam Safety, 1988 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 15)
    - Federal Issues, 1991-1992 (Box 15)
    - Fox River, 1988-1990 (Box 15)
    - Maumee River, 2003-2006 (Box 15)
    - Michigan Action Coalition, 1991 (Box 15)
    - Michigan Legislation, 1988; 1994 (Box 15)
    - Michigan Wetlands Management, 1990-1994 (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous Rivers, 1988 (Box 15)
    - Ott Preserve, 1994 (Box 15)
    - Portage Lake, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
    - State Natural Rivers Act, 1991 (Box 15)
    - Wild and Scenic Rivers, 1988-1992 (Box 15)
    - Wild and Scenic Rivers Bill, 1990 (Box 15)
    - General, 1998-2006 (Box 15)
- Legislation
  The Legislation series contains information on various legislation (federal and state) and document the club's position with respect to these bills and acts. The series covers mostly the late 1980's through the mid 1990's.
  - "Air Pollution Act", 1993
    - HB 4865 (Box 16)
    - HB 4166 (Box 16)
    - SB 46 (Box 16)
  - Amendment of Clean Air Act, SCR 339, 1994 (Box 16)
  - "Biological Diversity Conservation Act" (HB 4719), 1990-1992 (Box 16)
  - "Environmental Audit Privilege" (SB 728), 1995-1996 (Box 16)
  - In-the-District Lobby Month, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Joint Committee on Administrative Rules, 1987-1988 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Scenic Rivers Act
    - Hiawatha National Forest Statement of Agreement, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Background Materials, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Contact Lists, 1990 (Box 16)
    - HR 476 and HR 4019, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Government Publications and Information, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Maps and Figures, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Press Clippings, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Press Releases and Communications, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Rivers Hearing, 1990 (Box 16)
    - River Partner's Program, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Testimony and Resolutions, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club Correspondence, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club Press Releases, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club Notes, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club Recommendations and Testimony, 1990 (Box 16)
  - "Motor Fuels Quality Act" (HB 4898), 1993 (Box 16)
  - "Motor Vehicle Emissions Testing Program Act" (HB 5016), 1993 (Box 16)
  - Off-Road Vehicles
    - Correspondence
      - Sierra Club, 1989-1995 (Box 16)
      - Department of Natural Resources (DNR), 1990 (Box 16)
      - Legislative, 1990-1995 (Box 16)
      - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC), 1990-1991 (Box 16)
      - George and Robin Buchner, 1990-1995 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990; 1994 (Box 16)
    - Advisory Committee Minutes, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Draft DNR Plan and Comments, 1993 (Box 16)
    - Contact Lists, circa, 1990 (Box 16)
    - House and Senate Bills, 1989-1991 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC) Policy Meeting, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sierra Club Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - Press Clippings, 1989-1991 (Box 16)
  - "Polluter's Pay" (SB 375)
    - Correspondence
      - From Legislators, 1990 (Box 16)
      - Lobbying Organizations to Legislators, 1990 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Legislative Press Releases, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Legislative Votes, 1990 (Box 16)
    - HB 5878, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Lobby Day Logistics and Information Packets, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Lobby Organization Press Releases, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Lobby Day Participant Information, 1990 (Box 16)